American Psychological Association Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Boards and Committees, 1920-1986 (Box 292-549)
  - Ad hoc committees (Box 420)
    - Ethical Standards in Psychological Research
      - Correspondence
        - Drafts, regarding
          - Critiques
            - First draft from groups
              - Feb.-May 1972, 1973, undated (Box 425)
            - First draft from individuals, 1971, undated, (4 folders)
            - First draft prior to publication, 1971-1972, undated
            - Second published draft, 1972, (2 folders)
        - External, A-Z, 1966-1972, (4 folders) (Box 426)
        - Internal, B-S, 1965-1972, undated, (2 folders)
        - Memoranda, 1966-1972, undated, (2 folders)
      - Drafts (Box 427)
        - First draft of principles, Jan.-Feb. 1970
        - Second draft of principles, La Jolla, Calif., July 1970
        - Third working draft of principles, July-Aug. 1970
        - Fourth draft of principles, Aug.-Sept. 1970
        - Fifth draft of principles
          - Post-Boulder, Colo., 1970
          - Working
            - I-II, 1970
            - III, 1970, (3 folders) (Box 428)
        - Published
          - Circulated review, first publication of draft, 1971
          - First published in the Monitor, 1971, (2 folders)
          - Second draft (Box 429)
            - General, 1972, (2 folders)
            - Rough, undated, (2 folders)
          - Final version of ethics code, rough, 1972, (1 folder) (Box 430)
          - Final draft, undated, (2 folders)
        - Working revisions, 1972, (3 folders)
      - Miscellany (Box 431)
        - Drafts of letters, 1971-1972
        - Lists, 1970-1971
        - Miscellany, 1971, undated
        - Notes on speeches, 1971, undated
        - Parts of draft, I-IV, 1971
        - Preliminary pilot study, 1968
        - Questionnaire miscellany
          - Sample I and II, (2 folders)
          - Section of parts of drafts (Box 432)
          - Section 1.0--1.4, undated, (2 folders)
          - Section 1.5--6.5, (4 folders)
          - Topical suggestions, 1970
        - Reports, undated
      - Questionnaires, 1968 (Box 433)
        - Sample I
          - Miscellaneous problems
            - A. Compromising standards for financial gain
            - B. Continuing insignificant or irrelevant research in order to get or keep grant funds
          - Miscellany
            - General
          - Section I--Invasion of privacy
            - A. Asking questions of a personal nature
            - B. Obtaining information about persons from others
            - C. Studying persons who have no knowledge that they are subjects
            - D. Using recording devices to gain information
              - 1. With subject knowledge
              - 2. Without subject knowledge
            - E. Use of data banks
            - F. Disclosure of confidential information
              - 1. To unauthorized persons
              - 2. To superiors about subordinates
              - 3. To school or parents (Box 434)
              - 4. To police or court
              - 5. About captive populations
              - 6. In effort to aid subject
            - G. Failure to protect identity
              - 1. In publication of results
              - 2. By disclosing identity
              - 3. By determining identity without subjects' knowledge
          - Section II--Informed consent
            - A. With captive populations
              - 1. Students, (2 folders)
              - 2. Employees
              - 3. Mental employees (Box 435)
              - 4. Children
                - a. School v. parental consent
                - b. How much information should be given to parents
                - c. Appropriate questionnaires for minors
                - d. Allowing minors to decide for themselves
              - 5. Hospital patients
              - 6. Prisoners
              - 7. Members of military
            - B. In relation to nature of research
              - 1. Changing people's behavior
              - 2. Exposing people to psychological stress
              - 3. Exposing people to physical danger
            - C. Obtaining only partial consent
          - Section III--Deception
            - A. Deceptive statement of purpose
              - 1. To get subjects to participate
                - a. Subjects believe they will benefit
                - 1) Monetary reward
                - 2) Opportunity for employment
                - 3) Miscellaneous
                - b. Subjects would not participate otherwise
              - 2. In order to study real behavior
                - a. To induce natural behavior
                - b. To induce natural behavior under stress
            - B. Misleading feedback during the experiment (Box 436)
            - C. Concealing intent of indirect measures
            - D. Consequences of deception for psychological research
          - Section IV--Psychological stress
            - A. In deception studies
              - 1. Misleading feedback
                - a. Reflects poorly on subjects
                - b. Which produces anxiety
              - 2. Misleading instructions or explanation of purpose
            - B. Pressuring subject to behave in manner which could violate his morals
            - C. Exposing persons to situations which are embarrassing or stressful
            - D. Stressing subjects who have been inadequately screened
            - E. Inadequate follow-up and debriefing of subjects
            - F. Providing subjects with their own test of performance score
            - G. Dehumanization of subjects due to manipulative or condescending attitude by experimenter
            - H. Failure to recognize the special susceptibility of children to psychological stress
          - Section V--Physical stress
            - A. Use of electric shock
              - 1. Nonharmful use of electric shock
                - a. With normal adults
                - b. Subjects from psychology course
                - 1) Induced consent
                - 2) No prior knowledge of shock
              - 2. Dangerous use of electric shock
              - 3. Shock for behavior modification with subjects who may not be able to consent for themselves
              - 4. Electric shock (Incidents A,B,C,D)
            - B. Use of pain and food deprivation (Box 437)
              - 1. Procedures creating physical discomfort
                - a. With children
                - b. With mental patients
              - 2. Use of procedures creating excessive pain
              - 3. Informed consent to participate in experiment using pain
              - 4. Use of experimental procedures with potentially harmful physical consequences
              - 5. Incidents A and B
          - Section VI--Use of drugs
            - A. Use of potentially dangerous drug
              - 1. Not adequate prior evaluation
              - 2. Drugs known for bad effects on some subjects
                - a. With normal adults
                - b. With institutionalized patients
            - B. Informed consent to use drugs
              - 1. With normal adults
              - 2. To subjects who may not be able to give consent
            - C. Depriving controls of beneficial treatment in drug research
            - D. Incidents A,B,C,D
          - Section VII--Misuse of research results
            - A. In developing countries
              - 1. Invasion of privacy
              - 2. Cross-cultural difference
            - B. By federal and state agencies and the military
            - C. Misuse of research results
            - Incidents A,B,C,D
          - Section VIII--Research involving potential physical harm
          - Section IX--Exploitation of research subject
            - A. With general research subject
            - B. With minority groups
            - C. With control groups
        - Sample II
          - Section I--Invasion of privacy
            - A-B
            - C-G, (5 folders) (Box 438)
          - Section II--Informed consent (Box 439)
            - A. How informed subject must be
              - 1. Information given to subject, "a-c" miscellaneous
              - 2. Whose consent obtained? "a--b4" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
              - 3. Opportunity to refuse, "a-h" miscellaneous
              - 4. Timing of consent, "a-d" miscellaneous
            - B. Freedom of subject to decline after fully informed
              - 1. Type of coercion
                - "a" miscellaneous
                - "b-e" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 440)
          - Section III--Deception
            - A. Deceptive statement of purpose
              - 1. To get subjects to participate, "a-b" miscellaneous
              - 2. In order to study real behavior, "a-b" miscellaneous
            - B.-E.
          - Section IV--Psychological stress
            - A.-C., (2 folders)
            - D.-K., (3 folders) (Box 441)
          - Section V--Physical stress, A.-B.
          - Section VI--Use of drugs, A.-C.
          - Section VII--Possible misuse of research procedures and results
            - A.-C.
            - D.-F. (Box 442)
          - Section VIII--Use of experimental procedures with potentially harmful physical consequences
          - Section IX--Exploitation of research subjects, A.-D., (3 folders)
      - Subject file (Box 443)
        - Ethical codes
          - APA, 1953, 1959, 1963, 1968
          - Other organizations, 1965-1971
          - Ethical issues in psychological research, 1963-1970, undated, (2 folders)
          - Interviews, 1968, 1970, undated, (2 folders)
          - La Jolla, Calif., draft, notes on, July 1970
          - Source people, 1968-1969
    - International Congress of Psychologists, 1961-1964, (2 folders) (Box 444)
    - International exchange, 1967-1970
    - Local professional groups, 1965-1967
    - Manpower studies, 1966-1968
    - Mental retardation, 1962-1964
    - Occasional publications
      - Correspondence, 1966-1968, undated
      - Minutes and miscellany, 1966-1967
    - Organization of the APA (Box 445)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1978
      - Minutes, 1977
      - Miscellany, 1964-1970, 1976
      - Reports, 1977
    - Policy Regarding Identifying and Listing of Psychologists Services, 1960-1963, (2 folders)
    - Postdoctoral and Continuing Education
      - Correspondence
        - Advisory services, 1967-1971, (2 folders)
        - General, 1967-1970
        - Interest groups, 1966-1967
      - Fellowship announcement, selections, 1962-1968
      - Miscellany, 1963-1967
      - Reports
        - General, undated
        - Training needs, 1965 (Box 446)
    - Postdoctoral and Continuing Education
    - Practice and Social Consequences of Psychological Assessment
      - Correspondence, 1960-1965, (3 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1964
      - Reports and agenda, 1961-1965
    - Practice of Industrial Psychology, 1965
    - Professional Training (Box 447)
      - Correspondence
        - Conference, 1970
        - General
          - 1962, 1966, 1968
          - 1969-1971, (3 folders)
      - Minutes, 1969-1971
      - Reports, articles, proposals, 1965-1971
    - Promoting Public Interest Activity
      - Guidebook, 1977
      - Memoranda, 1974 (Box 448)
      - Minutes, 1974-1976
      - Reports, undated
    - Psychology and the Law, 1962-1964
    - Psychology and Its Relations with Other Professions, 1951-1954, undated, (3 folders)
    - Psychology and Its Relations with the Medical Profession, 1950-1953, undated, (3 folders)
    - Psychology Exhibit at the Chicago Museum of Science and Industry, 1959-1967, undated (Box 449)
    - Psychology in Governmental and Public Affairs
      - Agenda and reports, undated
      - Correspondence, 1953-1954, undated
      - Miscellany, 1953-1954
    - Public Affairs
      - Minutes, 1967
      - Miscellany, undated
      - Reports, 1959-1964
    - Public Information Center for Psychology, 1956-1958, undated, (2 folders)
    - Registration of Graduate Programs in Psychology
      - Background material, 1962-1963, undated
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - 1959, 1962
          - 1963, (4 folders) (Box 450)
        - Responses, accreditation procedures, letter of 31 Jan. 1963, (2 folders)
    - Relations with Sociology
      - Correspondence, 1957-1961, 1963
      - Meetings and minutes, 1957-1959
      - Memorandum, 1958-1962
      - Miscellany, 1958-1959, undated (Box 451)
      - Reports, 1959-1963, undated
    - Review of American Board for Psychological Services, 1958-1959, (2 folders)
    - Roles and Functions of Clinical Psychologists, 1965
    - Scientific and Professional Aims of Psychology
      - Agenda, 1963
      - Background material, 1955-1965
      - Correspondence
        - 1962-1964, (3 folders)
        - 1965-1967, 1969 (Box 452)
      - Miscellany, 1961-1965
        - General
        - State bills
      - Reports
        - 1961-1965
        - Undated (Box 453)
      - Statement of position, 1964
    - Social and Ethical Responsibilities
      - Nominations
        - Ballots, 21 Apr. 1977
        - Results, undated
    - Status of Counseling Psychology, 1958-1962, (3 folders)
    - Status of Women in Psychology
      - Agenda, minutes, and related material, 1973-1975
      - Correspondence, 1973-1974
      - Miscellany, 1973, undated
    - Structure and Function of Council (Box 454)
      - Correspondence
        - Drafts of letters, 1968-1969
        - General, 1967-1970, undated, (5 folders)
      - Minutes, 1968-1969
      - Miscellany, 1967-1970, undated
      - Reports, 1967-1970, undated
    - Subdoctoral Education
      - Articles, 1962
      - Correspondence
        - 1966-1967
        - 1968-1970 (Box 455)
      - Minutes, 1967-1968
      - Reports, proposals, summaries, and drafts, 1957, 1966-1969
      - Task Committee on Nondoctoral Education and Training, 1969-1970
      - Task Force on Manpower Demands and Training, 1970
      - Task Force on Master's Level Training, 1970, undated, (2 folders)
    - Two-Year College, 1971-1975, undated, (4 folders) (Box 456)
    - Utilizations of Psychologists, 1950-1956, undated, (5 folders)
    - Women in Psychology (Box 457)
      - Agenda and minutes, 1973
      - Correspondence, 1973-1974, (3 folders)
      - Miscellany, survey of women concerns, 1973
  - Continuing committees
    - Advisory Committee on Legislative Matters, 1950-1954, undated, (4 folders)
    - Advisory Committee on the Development and Status of Research and Education in Psychology
      - Correspondence
        - 1952-1953
        - 1954-1959, undated, (2 folders) (Box 458)
      - Reports, 1952-1957
    - APA Convention Committee, 1965
    - Building Committee, 1950-1954, (3 folders)
    - Committee on Academic Freedom, 1955, 1958
    - Committee on Academic Freedom and Conditions of Employment
      - Correspondence
        - 1949-1952
        - 1953-1958, (2 folders) (Box 459)
        - Reports and miscellany, 1953-1958, undated
        - Special cases, correspondence and reports, 1953-1955
    - Committee on Audio-Visual Aids
      - Correspondence, 1945-1954, (2 folders)
      - Minutes, reports, and miscellany, 1947-1953
    - Committee on Awards (best psychological paper), 1948-1949
    - Committee on Board of Examiners in Professional Psychology, 1946-1954, (3 folders) (Box 460)
    - Committee on Certification of Consulting Psychologists
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - A-L, 1922-1928, (3 folders)
          - M-Y, 1922-1927 (Box 461)
        - Regarding certifications, 1920-1922
        - With Brookline Trust Co., 1922-1924
    - Committee on Communication with High School Teachers
      - Correspondence, 1957-1963
      - Minutes, papers, and summaries, undated
    - Committee on Directory of Psychological Service Centers, 1948-1954, 1959-1960, 1976, (2 folders) (Box 462)
    - Committee on Doctoral Education, 1951-1958, undated, (4 folders)
    - Committee on Equality of Opportunity in Psychology
      - Agenda, 1963, 1969, 1975-1978
      - Annual reports, 1964-1966-1979 (Box 463)
      - Articles, 1963-1977, undated
      - Background correspondence
        - 1963-1976, (4 folders)
        - 1977-1979, undated, (3 folders) (Box 464)
      - Committee members
        - Correspondence, 1964, 1968, undated
        - Lists, 1967-1979, undated
      - Historical summary, 1977, undated
      - Lists, 1964, 1966-1967
      - Minutes, 1964-1979
      - Miscellany
        - Background material, 1964-1972, (1 folder) (Box 465)
      - Orientation packet, 1979
      - Papers, 1968-1977, undated
      - Proposals, 1969, 1977, undated
      - Reports
        - Draft, 1972
        - General, 1963-1978, undated
        - Subcommittee on Women, 1970 (Box 466)
      - Surveys, undated
    - Committee on Ethical Standards in Psychology
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - 1947-1955, (5 folders)
          - 1956-1962, (7 folders) (Box 467)
        - Regarding published code, 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 468)
      - Finances, correspondence and minutes, 1956-1959
      - Miscellany, 1949-1960, undated
      - Reports, 1948-1962, undated, (2 folders)
    - Committee on Ethical Standards of Psychologists
      - Correspondence
        - 1958-1959
        - 1960-1963, undated (Box 469)
    - Committee on Financial Problems of Divisions in Relation to APA, 1950-1952
    - Committee on Freedom of Inquiry
      - Agenda, minutes, and miscellany, 1954-1956
      - Correspondence, 1953-1956, (5 folders)
      - Reports, 1954-1956, undated
    - Committee on Graduate and Professional Training (Box 470)
      - Correspondence, 1945-1948, (3 folders)
      - Questionnaires, 1946-1947
      - Reports, 1946-1948, undated
    - Committee on Health and Accident Insurance
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - 1954-1963, (3 folders)
          - 1964-1970, undated, (3 folders) (Box 471)
        - With Liberty Mutual Insurance Co., 1955-1958, (3 folders)
      - Minutes and related material, 1958
      - Miscellany, undated, (3 folders) (Box 472)
      - Reports, 1954-1959
    - Committee on Health Insurance
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1962-1979, (2 folders)
        - Relating to legislation, 1962-1969 (Box 473)
      - Legislation
        - Accounts, and bills, 1959-1969
        - Miscellany, undated
      - Miscellany, 1964, 1970-1973, undated
      - Reports, 1963-1977
    - Committee on Implications of Atomic Energy for Psychology, 1947-1949
    - Committee on Insurance
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - Jan. 1959-Mar. 61, (2 folders)
          - Apr. 1961-Dec. 1963, (4 folders) (Box 474)
          - Jan. 1964-June 1966, undated, (3 folders) (Box 475)
      - Miscellany, 1961-1965
      - Reports and minutes, 1962, 1964, undated
    - Committee on Insurance and Related Social Development
      - Agenda and minutes, 1963-1968, undated
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - 1960-1962
          - 1963-1965, (5 folders) (Box 476)
          - 1966-1971, undated, (2 folders) (Box 477)
        - Regarding meetings, 1963-1967, (2 folders)
        - With committee members, 1962-1970, (2 folders)
        - With industry
          - AFL-CIO, 1964-1969
          - American Psychiatric Association, 1965-1968
          - Federal Government Employees Program, 1962-1968
          - Remington Rand, 1963-1964
          - United Auto Workers, 1965-1967
        - With insurance companies (Box 478)
          - Aetna Casualty and Surety Co., 1961-1964
          - Beneficial Standard Life Insurance Co., 1964
          - Blue Cross-Blue Shield, 1963-1969, undated
          - Liberty Mutual, 1963-1969
          - Medicare, 1965-1968, (2 folders)
          - Military Medical Benefits, 1967
          - Miscellaneous, 1959-1968, (2 folders)
          - Occidental Life Insurance Co., 1963-1968
          - Pennsylvania Mental Health Plan, 1967-1968
          - Prudential, 1965-1968
      - Insurance reimbursement forms (Box 479)
        - Completed questionnaires, 1964
        - Miscellany, 1964-1968, (3 folders)
        - Papers, 1964-1966, undated
        - Reports (Box 480)
          - General, 1963-1968, (2 folders)
          - Washington reports, 1964-1967
    - Committee on International Planning in Psychology
      - Correspondence
        - 1942-1947, (2 folders)
        - 1948-1952, undated, (2 folders) (Box 481)
      - Miscellany, undated
    - Committee on International Relations in Psychology
      - Conventions
        - 1977, San Francisco, Calif., 1976-1977, (2 folders)
        - 1978, Toronto, Ont., 1977-1978, undated
        - Miscellany, 1977-1978
      - Correspondence
        - 1946
        - 1947-1958, undated, (7 folders) (Box 482)
      - Minutes, 1947, 1978, 1982, undated (Box 483)
      - Miscellany, 1949, 1951, 1958, undated
      - Reports, 1945-1958
    - Committee on Intraprofessional Relationships in Psychology, 1949-1951, (2 folders)
    - Committee on Mathematical Training of Social Scientists, 1950-1955
    - Committee on Member Insurance
      - Correspondence
        - 1959-1963, (2 folders)
        - 1965, (2 folders) (Box 484)
      - Reports and miscellany, 1961-1964
    - Committee on Mental Health Programs
      - Articles and newsletters, 1956-1962, undated
      - Correspondence
        - 1953-1958, (4 folders)
        - 1959-1962, (5 folders) (Box 485)
        - Undated (Box 486)
      - Minutes, 1959-1960
      - Miscellany, 1956-1961, undated
      - Reports, 1955-1960, undated
      - Statements, surveys, and resolutions, undated
    - Committee on Mental Health Research and Programs
      - Articles and surveys, 1962-1965
      - Correspondence
        - 1958-1963, (2 folders)
        - 1964-1966, undated, (2 folders) (Box 487)
      - Drafts, 1964, undated
      - Minutes, 23 Oct. 1965
      - Reports, 1959, 1962-1965
      - Speeches, 1966
    - Committee on Opportunities for Retired Psychologists, 1953-1956
    - Committee on Organization and Function of State
      - Associations
        - Correspondence
          - 1959-1962, (4 folders)
          - 1963-1968, undated, (3 folders) (Box 488)
        - Handbook, 1958
        - Miscellany, 1958-1964, undated
        - Reports, 1959-1965
        - Surveys, 1959-1963
        - Symposiums, meetings, and workshops, 1961-1964, undated
    - Committee on Participation in APA Activities
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - Jan. 1953-Feb. 1954, (2 folders)
          - Mar. 1954-July 1955, (4 folders) (Box 489)
        - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 490)
      - Reports and miscellany, 1954, undated
    - Committee on Participation in Association Affairs, 1953-1954
    - Committee on Precautions in Animal Experimentation
      - Articles, undated
      - Correspondence, 1946-1958, 1971-1973, undated, (2 folders)
    - Committee on Precautions in Animal Experimentation, undated
    - Committee on Precollege Psychology
      - Agenda and minutes, 1969-1973
      - Correspondence
        - 1969-1972, (2 folders)
        - 1973-1976, (3 folders) (Box 491)
      - Miscellany, 1969-1977, undated
      - Proposals, 1967-1969
      - Reports, 1967-1973 (Box 492)
    - Committee on Private Practice
      - Correspondence, 1958-1962, undated, (5 folders)
      - Miscellany, undated
      - Reports and articles, 1958-1961
    - Committee on Professional Information of the Conference of Psychologist Directors in Mental Health Programs, salary data tables, 1966-1971
    - Committee on Professional Liability Insurance
      - Correspondence
        - 1951-1952
        - 1953-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 493)
      - Reports, 1952-1954, undated
    - Committee on Professional Standards, 1953, 1983
    - Committee on Psychological Tests and Assessment, 1954-1958, 1964-1967, 1976-1978, 1983, undated, (4 folders)